<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Immunol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2172</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24886325</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4013431</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2172-15-17</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2172-15-17</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin gene variants and infections in patients receiving autologous stem cell transplantation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A1"><name><surname>Moreto</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>anamoreto@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;as-Alvarez</surname><given-names>Concepci&#x000f3;n</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>cfarinas@humv.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Puente</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>puentepomposo@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Ocejo-Vinyals</surname><given-names>Javier Gonzalo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>jgocejo@humv.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Velasco</surname><given-names>Pablo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>pvelasco103@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Horcajada</surname><given-names>Juan Pablo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>JHorcajada@parcdesalutmar.cat</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Batlle</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mbatlle@humv.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8"><name><surname>Montes</surname><given-names>Carmen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>carmenmontesgaisan@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>Francisca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>fsantos@humv.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A10"><name><surname>Conde</surname><given-names>Eulogio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>eulogio.conde@unican.es</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A11"><name><surname>Fari&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>Maria-Carmen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>farinasc@unican.es</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Hematology, Hospital Universitario Marqu&#x000e9;s de Valdecilla, University of Cantabria, IFIMAV, Santander, Spain</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Health Care Quality Unit, Hospital Universitario Marqu&#x000e9;s de Valdecilla, University of Cantabria, IFIMAV, Santander, Spain</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Immunology, Hospital Universitario Marqu&#x000e9;s de Valdecilla, University of Cantabria, IFIMAV, Santander, Spain</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Infectious Diseases Unit, Hospital Universitario Marqu&#x000e9;s de Valdecilla, University of Cantabria, IFIMAV, Santander, Spain</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Current address: Department of Hematology, Hospital Universitario de Cruces, Bilbao, Spain</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Current address: Department of Infectious Diseases, Hospital Universitari del Mar, Barcelona, Spain</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Moreto et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Moreto et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2172/15/17"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Serious infections are common in patients undergoing autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT) mainly because of the effects of immunosuppression. The innate immune system plays an important role in the defense against different infections. Mannose binding lectin (MBL) is a central molecule of the innate immune system. There are several promoter polymorphisms and structural variants of the <italic>MBL2</italic> gene that encodes for this protein. These variants produce low levels of MBL and have been associated with an increased risk for infections.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Prospective cohort study. The incidence, severity of infections and mortality in 72 consecutive patients with hematologic diseases who underwent ASCT between February 2006 and June 2008 in a tertiary referral center were analyzed according to their <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype. INNO-LiPA <italic>MBL2</italic> was used for <italic>MBL2</italic> gene amplification and genotyping. Relative risks (RR) (IC95%) as measure of association were calculated. Multivariate analysis was performed using logistic regression.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A statistically significant higher number of fungal infections was found in patients with <italic>MBL2</italic> variants causing low MBL levels (21.1%versus1.9%, p=0.016). In this <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group infection was more frequently the cause of mortality than in the <italic>MBL2</italic> wild-type group (p=0.05). Although not statistically significant, there was a higher incidence of major infections in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group as well as a higher number of infections caused by gram-positive bacteria.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Low-producer <italic>MBL2</italic> genotypes were associated with an increased number of fungal infections in ASCT patients, which would suggest that MBL has a protective role against such infections. ASCT patients with <italic>MBL2</italic> variant genotypes are more likely to die as a result of an infection.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>MBL</kwd><kwd>Gene variant</kwd><kwd>Polymorphism</kwd><kwd>Infection</kwd><kwd>Autologous stem cell transplant</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Patients undergoing autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT) are at a high risk of serious infection, mainly due to both the procedure and the underlying disease requiring the transplant, which in most patients undergoing the procedure is hematological [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p>Mannose-binding lectin (MBL) is a circulating liver-synthesized C-type serum protein of importance in the innate immune defense system. It is one of the recognition molecules in the lectin complement activation pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Human MBL is derived from a single gene located on chromosome 10 (<italic>MBL2</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>Serum levels and the function of MBL oligomers are strongly influenced by genetic variants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Low levels of MBL have been associated with increased susceptibility to infections, especially in recurrent or severe forms, even in immunocompetent individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. However, isolated low MBL serum levels do not usually cause disease. This deficiency appears to be associated with severe infections when other immune deficiencies occur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>The effect of MBL deficiency in the infectious complications of patients receiving chemotherapy is variable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. It has been associated with serious infections and more prolonged episodes of febrile neutropenia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], as well as with an earlier first severe infection in deficient patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. There are also several studies which analyze the relationship between MBL and allogeneic stem cell transplantation infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], but until now, only two studies dealing with this issue in ASCT have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. The focus of this study is the association between <italic>MBL2</italic> gene variants and the risk of infections in patients with different hematologic diseases undergoing ASCT.</p><sec><title>Patients and methods</title><sec><title>Patients</title><p>A prospective cohort study of all patients who received an ASCT for hematologic disease from February 2006 to June 2008 in the Hospital Universitario Marqu&#x000e9;s de Valdecilla (1,000-bed teaching hospital) was performed. All transplanted patients &#x0003e;13&#x000a0;years old without immunodeficiency (solid tumors, HIV infection or congenital immunodeficiencies) were included. Patients were followed up after inclusion in the study for 6&#x000a0;months.</p></sec><sec><title>Infections</title><p>Intercurrent infections were monitored during the early period (0&#x02013;30 days after ASCT), the intermediate period (30&#x02013;100 days after ASCT) and the late period (&#x0003e;100&#x000a0;days after ASCT). Infections were prospectively collected by the clinical research associates from the institution using a standardized data collection form, following the protocols of the Hematology Department of the Hospital Universitario Marqu&#x000e9;s de Valdecilla, in compliance with the clinical guidelines of the Infectious Diseases Society of America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Prophylactic measures included isolation in high-pressure rooms with air filters and the administration of intravenous acyclovir at prophylactic doses from day -3. Antibiotics and antifungal prophylaxis were not routinely administered.</p><p>An infectious episode was defined as a microbiologically or clinically documented infection. Microbiologically documented infections with the same organisms during the same phase of therapy occurring more than 7&#x000a0;days apart were counted as different infections. Major infection was predefined as either sepsis confirmed on microbiological testing or a systemic inflammatory response syndrome with highly suggestive radiographic or clinical characteristics and the requirement for a specific antimicrobial treatment in both cases. The following conditions were excluded: single positive blood culture resulting from contaminant skin bacteria, upper respiratory tract infections, culture-negative interstitial pneumonitis, dermatological varicella zoster reactivation, and local herpes simplex reactivation. Severe herpes virus infection was predefined as invasive viral infections requiring prompt treatment and hospitalization. A positive cytomegalovirus (CMV) blood culture or CMV-pp65 antigenemia assay or polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for CMV DNA (&#x0003e;400 copies/ml) (COBAS Amplicor CMV Monitor, Roche Diagnostics) and symptoms of organ dysfunction were required to fulfill the criteria of a clinically significant CMV infection/reactivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Episodes of asymptomatic CMV reactivation, primary varicella zoster virus and Epstein-Barr virus infections were excluded.</p></sec><sec><title>MBL2 genotyping</title><p>Blood was collected in EDTA-stabilized tubes in compliance with approved protocols from our institution. Genomic DNA from patients and controls was extracted from peripheral blood by using the Maxwell 16 Genomic DNA Purification system. For <italic>MBL2</italic> gene amplification and genotyping, the INNO-LiPA <italic>MBL2</italic> (Innogenetics Diagnostica Iberia S.L.U, Barcelona, Spain) was used, following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The INNO-LiPA <italic>MBL2</italic> is a line probe assay, designed for genotyping the 6 variations in the human <italic>MBL2</italic> gene (-550G&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;C, -221G&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;C, +4C&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;T, R52C, G54D, and G57E), providing an analysis of the seven common haplotypes and the 28 possible resulting diplotypes.</p><p>Exon mutations called structural variants (normal allele or &#x0201c;wild-type&#x0201d; <italic>A</italic> and mutant alleles <italic>B</italic>, <italic>C</italic> and <italic>D</italic> which together were called allele <italic>O</italic>) and promoter polymorphisms (<italic>H/L</italic>, <italic>Y/X</italic> and <italic>P/Q</italic>) were analyzed. Variants <italic>YA/YA</italic>, <italic>XA/XA</italic> and <italic>YA/XA</italic> were classified as <italic>A/A</italic>. Those with any mutation in the exon such as <italic>YA/O</italic>, <italic>XA/O</italic> were classified as <italic>A/O</italic> and, lastly, individuals homozygous for the structural variants in the exon were considered as <italic>O/O</italic>. Thus, patients were divided in two groups according to their <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype: 1) normal homozygous patients (<italic>AA</italic>) and 2) patients with <italic>AO</italic> and <italic>OO</italic> genotypes, who were considered to be lower MBL producers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Results were analyzed according to <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype, comparing normal homozygous patients (<italic>AA</italic>) and patients with <italic>AO</italic> and <italic>OO</italic> genotype and to determine if there were differences between the two groups in terms of demographic characteristics, underlying disease, infection parameters and mortality. Statistical analysis was performed using a two-tailed <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> test and a Fisher&#x02019;s exact test, Student <italic>t</italic>-test or Mann Whitney, as appropriate in each case. For m&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;n tables, a Fisher&#x02019;s exact test was estimated using the Monte Carlo method. Relative risks (RR) and their 95% confidence intervals (CI) were calculated to analyze the association between genetic variants and polymorphisms and the risk of concomitant infections as dependent variables (overall and by microorganisms). Multivariate analysis was performed using logistic regression to estimate the association between genetic variants and polymorphisms and the risk of underlying infections adjusted by confusion factors. A regression model was constructed for each type of infection, with infection-related variables being the outcome and the independent variable being the <italic>MBL2</italic> genotypes, adjusted for sex, age, hematologic disease, active pre-transplant hematologic disease. A two-tailed P &#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant. Data were analyzed using Stata (SE 10.0, Stata Corporation, College Station, TX) and SPSS (version 19) (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL) statistical software.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethics</title><p>This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Autonomous Community of Cantabria, Spain. All patients (&#x0003e;18&#x000a0;years) signed informed consent to participate in the study. For children under 18&#x000a0;years, the parents had to sign informed consent.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title><bold>
<italic>MBL2</italic>
</bold> structural variants, promoter polymorphisms and genotypes</title><p>Seventy-two patients were included. Median age at the time of transplantation was 54&#x000a0;years (19&#x02013;74). During the study period, no patients under 19&#x000a0;years underwent AST. Forty-two (42) patients were men. Patients were divided in two groups according to their <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype: patients homozygous (<italic>AA</italic>) for wild type <italic>MBL2</italic> (n =&#x02009;53) and other patients, <italic>AO/OO</italic> (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19), which included heterozygous patients (<italic>AO</italic>) (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;16), and homozygous patients (<italic>OO</italic>) (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3). No statistically significant differences were found in both groups for gender, age, distribution according to different types of hematologic disease or hematologic disease activity at the time of transplantation. Patient characteristics, underlying disease and number of previous lines of treatment are shown in Tables&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics and MBL genotypes of 72 patients with ASCT</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>AA </italic>
</bold><bold>
<italic>Patients (%) n&#x02009;=&#x02009;53</italic>
</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>AO/OO </italic>
</bold><bold>
<italic>Patients (%) n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19</italic>
</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>P-value*</italic>
</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Gender</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<bold>Male</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">30 (56.6)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">12 (63.2)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.62<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<bold>Female</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">23 (43.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7 (36.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Mean age (SD), years</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">51.6 (13.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">50.2 (14.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.70<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Underlying disease</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.78<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;MM<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">14 (26.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6 (31.6)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;HD<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">8 (15.1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5 (26.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;NHL<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">22 (41.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7 (36.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;AMN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7 (13.2)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (5.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;PL<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;Amyloidosis<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Active disease**</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.22<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;YES<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">11 (20.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7 (36.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02009;NO</td><td align="left">42 (79.2)</td><td align="left">12 (63.2)</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>Two-tailed Chi-squared test/Fisher exact test for categorical variables or two-tailed t-test for continuous variables.</italic></p><p>**<italic>Active pre-transplant hematologic disease.</italic></p><p>MM: multiple myeloma, HD: Hodgkin disease, NHL: non Hodgkin lymphoma, AMN: acute myeloid neoplasia, PL: prolymphocytic leukemia, ME: multiple sclerosis.</p><p><italic>AA</italic> genotype: patients homozygous for wild-type structural allele (<italic>A</italic>).</p><p><italic>AO/OO</italic> genotype: patients heterozygous or homozygous for the <italic>B</italic>, <italic>C</italic> or <italic>D</italic> alleles.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Number of chemotherapy lines pre-transplant</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>AA </italic>
</bold><bold>
<italic>Patients (%) n&#x02009;=&#x02009;53</italic>
</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>AO/OO </italic>
</bold><bold>
<italic>Patients (%) n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19</italic>
</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>P-value*</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>0</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.18<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>1</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">14 (26.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5 (26.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>2</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">26 (49.1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10 (52.6)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>3</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">12 (22.6)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (10.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>4</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (10.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Mean (SD)</bold></td><td align="left">1.9 (0.8)</td><td align="left">2.1 (0.9)</td><td align="left">0.55</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Two-tailed Fisher&#x02019;s exact test for categorical variables or two-tailed t-test for continuous variables.</p><p><italic>AA</italic> genotype: patients homozygous for wild-type structural allele (<italic>A</italic>).</p><p><italic>AO/OO</italic> genotype: patients heterozygous or homozygous for the <italic>B</italic>, <italic>C</italic> or <italic>D</italic> alleles.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Infections</title><p>Episodes of infection were recorded from the first day after infusion (day +1) until the sixth month post-transplantation. The average number of episodes of infection per patient was 2 (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.3) with a minimum of 0 and a maximum of 8 (1 patient). A total of 138 episodes of infection were collected in 69 patients. Three (3) patients had no infections during follow-up (4.2%). Thirty-one (31) patients (43.1.%) had a single episode, 20 (27.8%) had 2 episodes, 11 (15.3%) 3 episodes, 4 (5.6%) 4 episodes, 2 (2.8%) 5 episodes and one patient (1.4%) had 8 episodes of infection.</p><p>There were 112 infections in the early period (from day 1 to 30), 17 in the intermediate period (days 31 to 100) and 9 in the late period (day 101 to the end of the study). An average of 1.74 (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.04) episodes of infection occurred in the wild-type <italic>MBL2</italic> group, and 2.42 (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.84) in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group, with a greater number of infections in the deficient group (at the limit of statistical significance, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.051).</p><p>Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> shows infection characteristics. Sepsis was common (43.1%) and equally distributed between both groups, as was urinary tract infection which occurred at a lower frequency (11.1%) than expected. There was also a low incidence of pneumonia (5.6% of all patients), which occurred more frequently in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group, 10.5% versus 3.8%, RR: 2.8 (0.4-18.4), <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.28. Venous catheter infection occurred at a similar rate in both groups; 11.3% versus 10.5%, risk ratio (RR): 0.9 [95% confidence interval (CI) 0.2-4.2, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.00].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><bold>
<italic>MBL2 </italic>
</bold><bold>genotypes and infections in 72 patients with ASCT during the 6&#x000a0;months of follow-up</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>AA</italic>
</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>AO/OO</italic>
</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>RR (95% CI)</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>P-value*</italic>
</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Patients (%)</italic>
</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Patients (%)</italic>
</bold><hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th><th align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>n&#x02009;=&#x02009;53</italic>
</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>n&#x02009;=&#x02009;19</italic>
</bold></th><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Types of Infection</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-Pneumonia<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (3.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (10.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.8(0.4-18.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.28<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-Sepsis<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">22 (41.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9 (47.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.1 (0.6-2.0)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.66<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-VCI<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6 (11.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (10.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.9 (0.2-4.2)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.00<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-UTI<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5 (9.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3 (15.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.7 (0.4-6.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.43<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Major infection</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6 (11.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5 (26.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.32 (0.80-6.74)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.15<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Gram-positive infections</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">14 (26.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9 (47.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.8 (0.9-3.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>0.09</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<italic>-S. epidermidis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9 (17)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">7 (36.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.2 (0.9-5.0)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.11<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<italic>-S. aureus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0 (0)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">--<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.00<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<italic>-Other</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Gram-negative infections</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">19 (35.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6 (31.6)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.9 (0.4-1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.74<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Viral infections</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (5.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.8 (0.2-42.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.46<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-CMV<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0 (0)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (5.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">--<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.26<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Fungal infections</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4 (21.1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">11.5 (1.3-93.7)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>0.016</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<bold>
<italic>-</italic>
</bold><italic>Candida</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1(1.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (10.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5.6 (0.5-58.1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.17<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<bold>
<italic>-</italic>
</bold><italic>Aspergillus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0 (0)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (5.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">--<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.26<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<italic>-Mucor</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0 (0)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (5.3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">--<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.26<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>N&#x000ba; deaths</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4 (7.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3 (15.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.1 (0.5-8.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.37<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Cause of death</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-Infection<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">--<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.05<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-Progression<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">--<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;&#x02009;-Unknown (not infection)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">--</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*<italic>Two-tailed Chi-squared test or Fisher exact test as corresponding.</italic></p><p>RR: risk ratio; CI: confidence interval.</p><p>VCI: Venous catheter infection; UTI: Urinary tract infection.</p><p><italic>AA</italic> genotype: patients homozygous for wild-type structural allele (<italic>A</italic>).</p><p><italic>AO/OO</italic> genotype: patients heterozygous or homozygous for the <italic>B</italic>, <italic>C</italic> or <italic>D</italic> alleles.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Fifteen major episodes of infection were recorded: sepsis in 8 patients; pneumonia in 5 patients, including one pulmonary aspergillosis and one Mucor pneumonia; and 2 patients with severe diarrheal episodes (one caused by <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic>). A higher incidence of major episodes of infection was observed in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group, 26.3% versus 11.3% in the <italic>MBL2</italic> wild-type group: RR&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.32, (95% CI: 0.80-6.74, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.15), although this did not reach statistical significance.</p><p>There were 68 microbiologically documented infections (50% of all the infections) in 39 patients. Fifty-six (82.4%) of these infections occurred in the early period, 5 (7.4%) in the intermediate and 7 (10.2%) in the late period. There were 33 infections caused by gram-positive bacteria, 36 caused by gram-negative bacteria, 5 fungal infections and 2 infections caused by virus. Eight were polymicrobial infections.</p><p>The average number of microbiologically documented infections was not statistically significant different between both groups, although there was a greater number of infections with microbiological documentation in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group: 1.32 (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.53) versus 0.81 (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.96 <italic>p&#x02009;=</italic>&#x02009;0.1).</p><p>There was a higher average of microbiologically documented episodes of infection in the early period in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group (1.90 (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.2), than in the <italic>MBL2</italic> wild-type (1.37 (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.2 <italic>p&#x02009;=</italic>&#x02009;0.062), but this did not reach statistical significance.</p><p>The average time in days until the first infection after the transplantation day was 7.98&#x000a0;days (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.34) in the wild-type <italic>MBL2</italic> group and 13&#x000a0;days (SD&#x02009;=&#x02009;30.73) in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32).</p><p>Regarding the type of infection, gram-positive bacteria were more frequent in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group, 47.4% versus 26.4%, RR&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.8 (95% <bold>CI</bold>: 0.9-3.4, <italic>p&#x02009;=</italic>&#x02009;0.09). There was a greater incidence of infections caused by <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group, 36.8% versus 17%, RR&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.2 (95% <bold>CI</bold>: 0.9-5.0, <italic>p&#x02009;=</italic>&#x02009;0.11). In the adjusted analysis, the odds ratio (OR) was 4.0 (95% <bold>CI</bold>: 1.0-16.5, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05), at the limit of statistical significance (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). There was only 1 case of infection by <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic>, in the <italic>MBL2</italic> wild-type group.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><bold>Association between </bold><bold>
<italic>MBL2 </italic>
</bold><bold>genotypes and infections: Multivariate analysis</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead valign="top"><tr><th align="left"><bold>Outcome variable (patients with infection)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>OR* (95% </bold><bold>CI) (Effect of </bold><bold>
<italic>MBL2 </italic>
</bold><bold>genotypes on risk of infection)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>
<italic>p-value</italic>
</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Types of infection</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-Pneumonia<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">8.1 (0.4-158.2)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.17<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-Sepsis<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.9 (0.3-3.1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.88<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-VCI<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.8 (0.1-5.0)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.77<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;-UTI<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.3 (0.4-12.8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.44<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Serious infection</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.8 (0.1-4.9)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.79<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Gram-positive infections</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2.5 (0.8-7.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.11<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02003;&#x02009;<italic>-S. epidermidis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4.0 (1.0-16.5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.05<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Gram-negative infections</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.7 (0.2-2.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.59<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>
<italic>Viral infections</italic>
</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1.1 (0.01-60.4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">0.96<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>
<italic>Fungal infections</italic>
</bold></td><td align="left">12.9 (1.1-153.9)</td><td align="left">0.03</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Odds Ratio (OR) adjusted by: sex, age, type of hematologic disease, active pre-transplant hematologic disease.</p><p>CI: confidence interval.</p><p>VCI: Venous catheter infection; UTI: Urinary tract infection.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Most infections caused by gram-positive bacteria occurred in the early period and were more frequent in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group (42.1% versus 26.4% in the <italic>MBL2</italic> wild-type group, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.2). There were no such infections in the intermediate period and only one in each group in the late period.</p><p>The incidence of fungal infections in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group (3 <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, 1 <italic>Mucor</italic>, 1 <italic>Aspergillus</italic>) was statistically significantly higher than in the <italic>MBL2</italic> wild-type group (1 <italic>Candida</italic> spp), RR&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.5 (95% CI: 1.3-93.7, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.016), as confirmed in a multivariate analysis (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>).</p><p>There were no statistically significant differences in the incidence of infection caused by gram-negative bacteria, RR: 0.9 (95% <bold>CI</bold>: 0.4-1.9, <italic>p&#x02009;=</italic>&#x02009;0.74), or by virus between both groups, RR: 2.8 (95% <bold>CI</bold>: 0.2-42.4, <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.46), although there was a higher incidence of viral infections in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group.</p><p>More patients died in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group than in the wild-type <italic>MBL2</italic> group (15.8% versus 7.5% respectively, <italic>p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.37</italic>), although this difference was not statistically significant. However, all deaths in the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> group were related to infection, whereas in the wild-type <italic>MBL2</italic> group, deaths were due to other causes, with a <italic>p</italic>-value of 0.05 at the limit of statistical significance (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>This prospective study focused on comparing the incidence of infection and mortality after ASCT between patients with the wild-type <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype compared to patients carrying a variant <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype. The <italic>MBL2</italic> variant is associated with lower levels of serum MBL, so it may be related with a greater number of infections and/or more serious infections. A multivariate analysis was performed to rule out other factors that could cause a higher incidence or severity of infection (disease status-response <italic>vs</italic>. type of hematologic disease, active pre-transplant hematologic disease, sex and age).</p><p>The study group was homogeneous, with no differences in age, gender or hematologic disease, and presented similar disease activity at the time of transplantation.</p><p>So far, there are few studies describing the incidence of infections in ASCT related to <italic>MBL2</italic> gene variants. Horiuchi et al<italic>.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] in a series of 113 patients treated with high-dose chemotherapy and ASCT, most of whom had hematologic diseases, carried out a study of the incidence of major bacterial infection in patients with low-producing genotypes compared to the wild-type genotype, finding an association between the low-producing genotypes and a highly increased and significant risk of major bacterial infections. The incidence of major bacterial infections (9%) was lower than that observed in the current study (18%). This could be related with the use of prophylactic antimicrobials including ciprofloxacin and fluconazole in all their patients, in contrast to the usual practice in our center.</p><p>M&#x000f8;lle <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], in a retrospective study compared <italic>MBL2</italic> gene variants with the risk of severe infections in multiple myeloma in patients receiving ASCT after high-dose melphalan. They found that patients homozygous for wild-type <italic>MBL2</italic> had a significantly reduced risk of septicemia compared to patients carrying the variant <italic>MBL2</italic>. In our series, no differences were found in the number of patients with sepsis between the two groups. Although the lack of association between these infections and <italic>MBL2</italic> gene variants could be explained by the sample size, this could also be due to the different underlying diseases: in M&#x000f8;lle&#x02019;s study, all patients were diagnosed with multiple myeloma while our patients had heterogeneous hematologic diseases and therefore could have had a higher risk of infection. They also found more severe infections in patients with variant <italic>MBL2</italic>, although the differences were not statistically significant. Similarly, in our series more severe infections and a greater number of episodes of pneumonia were found in patients with variant <italic>MBL2</italic>.</p><p>When the incidence of infections caused by different microorganisms was analyzed, a higher number of infections caused by gram-positive bacteria was found in patients carrying the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> form, and these were mainly staphylococci. In this respect, the incidence of infections caused by <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> was greater in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group. These findings contrast with the similar number of central venous catheter infections found in both groups. This could mean that the increased number of infections caused by <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> is not only due to catheter infection. ASCT patients carrying the variant <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype, with MBL deficiency, may develop more <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> infections. However, the mechanism for this difference is unclear. A study by Hellemann et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] in critically ill patients admitted to an intensive care, showed an association between the <italic>MBL2 O/O</italic> genotype with an increased incidence of gram-positive infections. However, in two different studies by Neth et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] and Shang et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>], <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> generally demonstrated low MBL binding activity, which would contradict the hypothesis that MBL plays an important role in infections caused by <italic>S. epidermidis</italic>. One explanation that has been proposed for the diversity between the different studies may rely on the fact that MBL also functions as a scavenger molecule in maintaining internal tissue homeostasis. Apparent MBL associations may be due to disturbances in this scavenger system, rather than a direct antiinfectious effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>In the current study, no differences were found in the incidence of infections caused by gram-negative bacteria in patients with wild-type <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype <italic>versus</italic> patients carrying a variant <italic>MBL2</italic> genotype. This is consistent with the studies by Hellemann [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] and Sutherland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. There was only one case of viral infection in each group; in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant group this was caused by CMV, a potentially very serious disease, while the virus in the <italic>MBL2</italic> wild-type group was a reactivation of varicella zoster, which is more common in hematological patients.</p><p>Granell et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] showed that MBL pathway dysfunction due to genetically determined deficiencies of MBL influence the outcome of allogenic stem cell transplantation by increasing susceptibility to fungal invasive infections. In patients with ASCT, Horiuchi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] found that 3 of the 16 patients with major infections who had a pulmonary aspergillosis were homozygous for <italic>A</italic>, i.e. the normal <italic>MBL</italic> allele. On the contrary, in our study, 4 patients with fungal infection carried the <italic>MBL2</italic> deficient genotype; 2 had <italic>Aspergillus</italic> and <italic>Mucor</italic> pneumonia (both died as a consequence of their fungal infection); 1 had candidemia; and 1 had disseminated mucocutaneous <italic>Candida</italic> infection. Several studies have been published showing that MBL may play a crucial role in the innate immunity against yeast infections by increasing PMN uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>].</p><p>In our series, the incidence of mortality due to infection was higher in the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant form, and the cause of death in all patients was major infection. These findings are in line with other groups of immunosuppressed patients who had low-producing <italic>MBL2</italic> genotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, the results of our study suggest that ASCT patients with the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant gene have increased fungal infections, which would suggest that MBL offers protection against such infections. It would be reasonable to assess whether early antifungal prophylaxis in our ASCT patients with the <italic>MBL2</italic> variant gene could reduce the incidence of such infections. Due to the contradictory results of the previous reports, further studies are needed to clarify whether low-producing <italic>MBL2</italic> genotypes could play a role in gram-positive infections, especially in <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> infections. ASCT patients with <italic>MBL2</italic> variant genotypes are more likely to die as a result of an infection.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>ASCT: Autologous stem cell transplantation; MBL: Mannose binding lectin; CMV: Cytomegalovirus; RR: Relative risk; CI: Confidence interval; OR: Odds ratio.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interest</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>AM participated in data collection and manuscript preparation. CF-A participated in the design of the study, performed the statistical analysis and reviewed and revised the manuscript. MP participated in collection of data and manuscript preparation. JGO-V carried out part of the <italic>MBL2</italic> genotyping, and revised the manuscript. PS-V carried out part of the <italic>MBL2</italic> genotyping and revised the manuscript. JPH participated in the design of the study and reviewed and revised the manuscript. AB participated in collection of data. CM participated in collection of data and manuscript preparation. FS participated in collection of data and manuscript preparation. EC reviewed and revised the manuscript. MCF: participated in the design of the study, data analysis and reviewed and revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; information</title><p>Drs. Fari&#x000f1;as-Alvarez, Ocejo-Vinyals, Horcajada, Conde and Fari&#x000f1;as share senior authorship in this study.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are in debt with J.D. Garc&#x000ed;a-Palomo&#x02020; (Infectious Diseases Unit, H. Universitario Marques de Valdecilla, Santander, Spain) for his contribution to the study design and data analysis.</p><p>This work was supported by a grant from the Fondo de Investigaciones Sanitarias [FIS PI04/0492].</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bodey</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathe</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Freireich</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><article-title>Quantitative relationships between circulating leukocytes and infection in patients with acute leukemia</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>1966</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>340</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-64-2-328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5216294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pizzo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><article-title>Management of fever in patients with cancer and treatment-induced neutropenia</article-title><source>New Engl J Med</source><year>1993</year><volume>328</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199305063281808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8469254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schimpff</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><article-title>Empiric antibiotic therapy for granulocytopenic cancer patients</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>1986</year><volume>80</volume><issue>Suppl. 5C</issue><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3521270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Klastersky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Febrile neutropenia</article-title><source>Curr Opin Oncol</source><year>1993</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001622-199307000-00002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8364078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Groeger</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaler</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedlander-Klar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiehn</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Infectious morbidity associated with long-term use of venous access devices in patients with cancer</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>1993</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>1168</fpage><lpage>1174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-119-12-199312150-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8239247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Minchinton</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><article-title>Impact of mannose-binding lectin on susceptibility to infectious diseases</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1496</fpage><lpage>1505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/379324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14614673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sastry</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Herman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Deignan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruns</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezekowitz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><article-title>The human mannose-binding protein gene. Exon structure reveals its evolutionary relationship to a human pulmonary surfactant gene and localization to chromosome 10</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1989</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>1175</fpage><lpage>1189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.170.4.1175</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2477486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee Bouwman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bart Roep</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin: clinical implications for infection, transplantation, and autoimmunity</article-title><source>Hum Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humimm.2006.02.030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16720204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin (MBL) in health and disease</article-title><source>Immunobiology</source><year>1998</year><volume>199</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>339</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0171-2985(98)80037-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9777416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Waheed</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitman</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrad</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brett</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hinds</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin polymorphisms in severe sepsis: relationship to levels, incidence, and outcome</article-title><source>Shock</source><year>2006</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16369192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frederiksen</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensenius</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><article-title>Clinical manifestations of mannan-binding lectin deficiency</article-title><source>Mol Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molimm.2005.06.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16023210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Peterslund</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensenius</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Association between deficiency of mannose binding lectin and severe infections after chemotherapy</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2001</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>638</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(01)05785-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11530153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neth</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hann</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><article-title>Deficiency of mannose-binding lectin and burden of infection in children with malignancy: a prospective study</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2001</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>614</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(01)05776-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11530147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vekemans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgala</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heymans</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Muanza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Paesmans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klastersky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barette</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meuleman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Huet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Calandra</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrant</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathissen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Low mannose-binding lectin concentration is associated with severe infection in patients with hematological cancer who are undergoing chemotherapy</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2007</year><volume>44</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1593</fpage><lpage>1601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/518171</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17516403</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Osthoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rov&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Danner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gratwohl</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tichelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Trendelenburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin levels and major infections in a cohort of very long-term survivors after allogenic stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Haematologica</source><year>2010</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>1389</fpage><lpage>1396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3324/haematol.2009.017863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20418242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen-Hoogendijk</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Zijde CM</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Tol</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredius</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin levels and infections in children after allogeneic hematopoietic SCT</article-title><source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source><year>2010</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/bmt.2009.159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19597428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mullighan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heatley</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Danner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradstock</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Minchinton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarer</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Szer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardy</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin status is associated with risk of major infection following myeloablative sibling allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2008</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>2120</fpage><lpage>2128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2007-07-100222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18552214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Granell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbano-Ispizua</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Suarez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Avil&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uriburu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaya</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roncero</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carreras</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mensa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vives</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Montserrat</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Mannan-binding lectin pathway deficiencies and invasive fungal infections following allogeneic stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Exp Hematol</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1435</fpage><lpage>1441</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.exphem.2006.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16982337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kilpatrick</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>McLintock</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holyoake</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><article-title>Successful haemopoietic stem cell transplantation does not correct mannan-binding lectin deficiency</article-title><source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source><year>2005</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bmt.1704746</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15543198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mullighan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardy</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin and infection following allogeneic hemopoietic stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Leuk Lymphoma</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/1042819031000146983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15101708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Porcher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittencourt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>WA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Latouche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Devergie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Esperou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Socie</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zago</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gluckman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Host defense and inflammatory gene polymorphisms are associated with outcomes after HLA-identical sibling bone marrow transplantation</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2002</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>3908</fpage><lpage>3018</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2002-04-1033</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12393699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mullighan</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Heatley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarer</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Szer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tait</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bik To</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardy</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin gene polymorphisms are associated with major infection following allogeneic hemopoietic stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>3524</fpage><lpage>3529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.V99.10.3524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11986203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gondo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyagawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagafuji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takase</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitoma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamimoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyagi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tahira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimura</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Association of MBL gene polymorphisms with major bacterial infection in patients treated with high-dose chemotherapy and autologous PBSCT</article-title><source>Genes Immun</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.gene.6364165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15674393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>M&#x000f8;lle</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterslund</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffensen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>MBL2 polymorphism and risk of severe infections in multiple myeloma patients receiving high-dose melphalan and autologous stem cell transplantation</article-title><source>Bone Marrow Transplant</source><year>2006</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>555</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bmt.1705466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16953214</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><article-title>IDSA clinical practice guideline for the use of antimicrobial agents in neutropenic patients with cancer</article-title><comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.idsociety.org/Antimicrobial_Agents/#Neutropenic%20Patients%20with%20Cancer">http://www.idsociety.org/Antimicrobial_Agents/#Neutropenic%20Patients%20with%20Cancer</ext-link> (Accesed on 13 February 2013)</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Razonable</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Paya</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><article-title>Role of the laboratory in diagnosis and management of cytomegalovirus infection in hematopoietic stem cell and solid-organ transplant recipients</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.40.3.746-752.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11880387</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hellemann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonde</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarl&#x000f8;v</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetterslev</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garred</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Heterozygosity of mannose-binding lectin (MBL2) genotypes predicts advantage (heterosis) in relation to fatal outcome in intensive care patients</article-title><source>Hum Mol Genet</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3071</fpage><lpage>3080</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddm265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17872904</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Neth</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Jack</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Holzel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin binds to a range of clinically relevant microorganisms and promotes complement deposition</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2000</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>688</fpage><lpage>693</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.68.2.688-693.2000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10639434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><article-title>The binding of MBL to common bacteria in infectious diseases of children</article-title><source>J Zhejiang Univ SCI B</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1631/jzus.2005.AS0053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15593393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nauta</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Raaschou-Jensen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daha</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Borrias-Essers</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryder</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garred</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin engagement with late apoptotic and necrotic cells</article-title><source>Eur J Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>2853</fpage><lpage>2863</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.200323888</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14515269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Walley</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><article-title>Polymorphisms in CD14, mannose-binding lectin, and Toll-like receptor-2 are associated with increased prevalence of infection in critically ill adults</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.CCM.0000156242.44356.C5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Asbeck</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Andy IM</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jelle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Herpers</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose binding lectin plays a crucial role in innate immunity against yeast by enhanced complement activation and enhanced uptake of polymorphonuclear cells</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-8-229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19094203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Till</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Modderman</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Beld</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Boermeester</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>Mannose-binding lectin deficiency facilitates abdominal Candida infections in patients with secondary peritonitis</article-title><source>Clin Vaccine Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CVI.00297-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17978009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cervera</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balderramo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Su&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Prieto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuster</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Linares</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Navasa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Donor mannose-binding lectin gene polymorphisms b influence the outcome of liver transplantation</article-title><source>Liver Transpl</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1217</fpage><lpage>1224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lt.21834</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19790141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>